<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://emharsha1812.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://emharsha1812.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-09-12T13:58:03+00:00</updated><id>https://emharsha1812.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Let’s Build an LLM (from scratch)</title><link href="https://emharsha1812.github.io/blog/2024/lets-build-a-llm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Let’s Build an LLM (from scratch)"/><published>2024-09-11T00:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-11T00:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emharsha1812.github.io/blog/2024/lets-build-a-llm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emharsha1812.github.io/blog/2024/lets-build-a-llm/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>What I cannot create, I do not understand ~ Richard Feynman</p> </blockquote> <p>With the advent of LLMs, it has become imperative for any Machine learning engineer to understand and learn what they are and how they can be leveraged. I too want to learn about them</p> <p>This project is an effort to build a large language model from scratch, with the purpose of understanding LLMs from the ground up, how they are built, how they can be fine tuned and how can they be tinkered with</p> <p>For this project I will be using the book, <a href="https://www.manning.com/books/build-a-large-language-model-from-scratch">Build a Large Language Model</a> from Scratch by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sebastianraschka/">Sebastian Raschka</a>. I will also be attaching more links that I find useful.</p> <p>The projects base repository and all the content will be posted <a href="/projects/llm/">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="llm,machine-learning,python"/><category term="llm,python,machine-learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My attempt at building a large language model]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Visit to Hungarian Mathematics</title><link href="https://emharsha1812.github.io/blog/2024/hungarian-mathematics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Visit to Hungarian Mathematics"/><published>2024-09-01T00:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-01T00:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emharsha1812.github.io/blog/2024/hungarian-mathematics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emharsha1812.github.io/blog/2024/hungarian-mathematics/"><![CDATA[<p>Because my domain is machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI), it’s quite common for me to come across abstract mathematical equations that initially made no sense to me. However, as I dove deep into those arcane-looking symbols, I discovered another interesting thing aside from the meaning: I realized that most of the founders of these equations were from Hungary!</p> <p>I googled, and then, a few clicks later, I stumbled on this very interesting read titled <strong>‘A Visit to Hungarian Mathematics’</strong>. Here’s the <a href="https://gwern.net/doc/math/1993-hersh.pdf">link</a> 🔗 to this pape . It contained exactly what I was looking for; a detailed introspection into Hungarian mathematicss and the mathematicians surrounding them. While reading the paper, I found a very simple but profoundly impactful quote that I would like to share. It says</p> <blockquote> <p>Everyone has ideas, both right ideas and wrong ideas. Scientific work consists merely of seperating them</p> </blockquote> <p>I immediately started voraciously reading the paper from top to bottom, left to right, and backwards too. Even though I am not a mathematician and do not have a mathematics degree (although I have a fairly good amount of mathematical exposure), I love to explore mathematics as a hobby. I sincerely hope that my interest in mathematics is still relevant.</p> <p>One of the key takeaways from this paper will be a quote by Alfred Renyi, a Hungarian mathematician known for his work in probability theory, combinatorics, and other fields. Once, a gifted mathematician told him that his working ability was heavily dependent on external circumstances. Renyi responded,</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>“When I’m unhappy, I use math to find happiness; when I’m content, I use math to maintain my happiness.”</strong></p> </blockquote> <p>Reading about these mathematicians and their passion for pondering, fighting, and finally solving math problems fills me with a deep sense of gratitude towards math.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="mathematics,culture"/><category term="mathematics,"/><category term="axioms"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why Hungarians are so darn good at mathematics ?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome!</title><link href="https://emharsha1812.github.io/blog/2024/welcome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome!"/><published>2024-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emharsha1812.github.io/blog/2024/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emharsha1812.github.io/blog/2024/welcome/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hi! My name is Harshwardhan Fartale. I am an Active Machine learning enthusiast. I studied electrical engineering at National Institute of Technology, Hamirpur and currently serving as a project associate at Indian Institute of Science Bangalore.]]></summary></entry></feed>